<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tri V Nguyen</title>
    <link>https://trivnguyen.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Tri V Nguyen</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2019</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Apr 2019 13:14:25 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="https://trivnguyen.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Estimating the Sensitivity of IceCube to Signatures of Axion Production in a Galactic Supernova</title>
      <link>https://trivnguyen.github.io/publication/icrc_axion/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Apr 2019 13:14:25 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://trivnguyen.github.io/publication/icrc_axion/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DeepClean</title>
      <link>https://trivnguyen.github.io/project/deepclean/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2019 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://trivnguyen.github.io/project/deepclean/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Laser Interferometer Gravitational-Wave Observatory (LIGO) detects GWs by measuring the
induced differential arm length between its two perpendicular arms. Since its sensitivity upgrade
in 2016, LIGO has successfully detected many GW sources from black-hole to neutron-star mergers. However,
due to a number of noise sources, the detectors are currently operating below their design sensitivity.
These sources are instrumental and environmental effects, each coupling to the signal via a different
(both linear and non-linear) mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;noise_budget.png&#34; /&gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  &lt;h4&gt;LIGO Livingston Noise Budget. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ligo.org/science/Publication-O1Noise/index.php&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h4&gt;
  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LIGO currently relies on the Wiener filter to remove noise sources. However, the Wiener filter fails
to remove the non-linear contributions. Characterizing these non-linear contributions and removing them
using standard statistical and signal processing techniques can be challenging if not impossible because the
mechanisms are often complex and involved multiple noise channels. In this study, we use a machine learning
algorithm called the Long Short-Term Memory neural network to learn and filter out these non-linear noise sources.&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;lstm.png&#34; /&gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  &lt;h4&gt;Schematic of an LSTM layer. &lt;a href=&#34;https://colah.github.io/posts/2015-08-Understanding-LSTMs/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h4&gt;
  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first got involved in this project as a SURF student at LIGO Caltech in the summer of 2018, and have been continued
it since. DeepClean, our noise regression framework, is currently being developed by me, my mentor
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.michaelwcoughlin.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Michael Coughlin&lt;/a&gt;, and co-mentor
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.physics.umn.edu/people/ormiston.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Rich Ormiston&lt;/a&gt;. I developed the Tensorflow frontend/backend
and the Bayesian hyperparameter framework for DeepClean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my SURF final report, please click &lt;a href=&#34;deepclean.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For DeepClean repository (may require LIGO authentification), please click &lt;a href=&#34;$url_code&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>KITCAT</title>
      <link>https://trivnguyen.github.io/project/kitcat/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2019 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://trivnguyen.github.io/project/kitcat/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The early universe consists of a hot and dense photon-baryon plasma. Small density fluctuations in the plasma give
rise to acoustic sound waves. These sound waves are driven by radiation pressure and propagate at a relativistic
speed. About 400,000 years after the Big Bang, the universe is cool enough for free electrons to be captured
by protons to form neutral hydrogen atoms. These newly-formed hydrogen atoms do not interact strongly with photons, and,
as a result, photons decouple from the matter. No longer supported by radiation pressure, the baryon sound waves
halt, producing density bumps, often called the baryon acoustic oscillations (BAOs), at about $100 h^{-1}Mpc$ detectable in
the anisotropy of the cosmic microwave background (CMB) and in the distribution of galaxies.&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;density_profile.jpg&#34; /&gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  &lt;h4&gt;Evolution of the density profile due to acoustic sound waves in the early universe. &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/astro-ph/0604361&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h4&gt;
  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because BAOs create an excess of galaxies at about $100 h^{-1}Mpc$, they can be detected by studying at the large-scale clustering
of galaxies. To do this, physicists often use the spatial two-point correlation function (TPCF). The TPCF is a
mathematical tool to contrast between the observed distribution of galaxies and the distribution in which all galaxies
are uniformly distributed over the observed volume (referred to as the random distribution). It describes the excess
probability (observed over random) of finding two galaxies separated by some separation variables
(e.g. distance, angle). With this, BAOs should create a small bump in the spatial TPCF at about 150 Mpc.&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;tpcf.png&#34; /&gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  &lt;h4&gt;Evolution of the density profile due to acoustic sound waves in the early universe. &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/astro-ph/0604361&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h4&gt;
  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KITCAT, short for the Kd-tree Implementation for Two-point Correlation AlgoriThm, is a simple and fast tool to compute
the 1-D and 2-D spatial TPCF of galaxies. By assuming the random distribution can be separated into angular variables
(declination and right ascension) and redshift, KITCAT uses convolution of probability distributions to accelerate
the computation of the TPCF. Thanks to this, KITCAT also allows for a fast and flexible scan over the cosmological
parameter space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information, refer to &lt;a href=&#34;kitcat.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;this paper&lt;/a&gt; on which KITCAT is based.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For KITCAT v2.0.0: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/DESI-UR/KITCAT&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.2640917&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Zenodo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Extending the reach of gravitational-wave detectors with machine learning</title>
      <link>https://trivnguyen.github.io/talk/aas2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Jan 2019 10:40:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://trivnguyen.github.io/talk/aas2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
